this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer or software
hello everyone welcome to se radio today
with me you Looney once's new audiences
is the founder and the CEO of data
science workshop which provides on job
training and coaching data visualization
machine learning and programming
previously yeo-hoon was a data scientist
at Elsevier and answer them and startups
why plan and Outbrain in New York City
he has a master's degree in artificial
intelligence from Mystique's University
and a PhD in machine learning from
Tilburg University he is also the author
of data science at the command line
which was published by a really Reilly
media welcome to the show you hood Thank
You Felina thank you for having me the
topic of today is data science of course
the first question I have what exactly
is data science aha
yes so I think if you ask a dozen people
what data science means you probably get
back 13 different answers and so I don't
think I can give you an exact definition
of what data science is but the
definition that I like to use is simply
extracting value from data and this this
value can come in in basically two
different forms either it's an analysis
that you create and then the value comes
from making a decision based on this
analysis having or having additional
insight into your data or your certain
processes or aspects of your company and
the other form in which this value can
come is when you integrate data signs
into your product or your service and an
example that everybody knows is a
recommender system insane Netflix or
Amazon so that is the definition that I
like to use yeah so it's about getting
value
Dayna right right so there are other
forms of course of getting value from
data and an idea that comes to mind is
statistics statistics is also making
decisions based on data yeah is data so
in statistics or is something else
mm-hmm it is sistex is as I see it a
part of data science and to be honest
with you I I recently had to to look up
again what is being meant with
statistics so I opened up a well-known
statistics books book to look at the
contents and what I noticed there are
topics like distributions hypothesis
testing actually a whole range of tests
and I'm sure that if you have followed a
statistics course that this is what what
most comes to mind
things like correlation doing regression
and this is definitely an important part
of doing data science but it's it's not
everything if you pick up a typical data
science book then you'll see that it
also talks about getting this data in
the first place how to deal with data
that is messy that is complex and how do
you get it into the right shape how do
you create a visualization out of this
so in that sense they're not equal but
they're definitely related to each other
yeah so you're saying that statistics is
a part of data science what are other
parts of data science that aren't
statistics right so here I always like
to use a very pragmatic model of what
what data science is and this is one
created by Hilary Mason and Chris
Wiggins back in 2010 and they say they
propose the awesome model where awesome
is an abbreviation of five steps right
so and they say that data science
basically comes down to obtaining data
right without any data there's little
data science that you can
and then rarely does this data come in a
form that you can readily use so you
have to scrub this or clean this then
it's time to explore this data what does
it look like can you compute some
aggregate statistics make some quick
visualization and this could be the
result of itself right if you produce if
you're producing an analysis putting all
the data that you have in a in a
visualization could already be a
valuable thing sometimes you want to go
a step further and that is the modeling
data part of awesome so this is where
you may want to apply machine learning
or statistics right just to come back to
how those two are related to each other
to generate classifications to make
predictions into the future to see
whether there are any clusters or
patterns in your data
that's why machine learning is often
also known as pattern recognition and
then the last step according to the
awesome model is interpreting data how
what do your results mean how should you
interpret them how do you communicate
them back to your your colleagues or
your peers or your manager and of course
these five steps it's never as easy as
this sometimes you do these steps in
parallel sometimes you have to go back
because you notice that you're missing
some data or you made a mistake early on
but that is a very pragmatic I would say
set of things that you need to do in
order to do data science yes so you're
saying data science is broad it's not
just analyzing the data or doing
statistics is also obtaining the data
scrubbing and exploring it's all part of
the big umbrella of data science right
that's right if you say yeah no well I
was I was just thinking it's actually
too broad and that's also why I think
that there
there is this this term data science I'm
not a I'm not a big fan of it
I I don't really like the term science
in data science but but so far I haven't
been able to come up with it with a
better term yeah and sometimes the term
just it is there so even if we don't
agree it's it's something that everyone
says but I do want to come back to what
you're saying because one of my
questions I had in mind was being a
scientist myself what is science about
it can we can we apply it in a business
context or is this really something only
a scientist would do hmm
so I think data science is definitely
applicable in a business setting in fact
this is one of the few fields where I
see the industry and academia and
business coming together so because
businesses first of all had have a lot
of data and they also have a lot of
money to hire the people to work with
that data and while data science doesn't
necessarily have to be scientific at all
if you if you build a recommendation
system right that in itself is not
really scientific right if there's no
hypotheses associate with it if you're
not doing well well so what is what is
science really that's a bit too deep
maybe it is perhaps a bit too deep but
it is there's definitely the part where
you depending again on the type of data
science that you're doing either
analyzing or or building something it
could be that you have an AI pollicis
that you experiment that you make
observations draw conclusions from that
but that's not necessarily the case and
maybe that's that's the biggest
difficulty I have with the term because
it that there are these two categories
there is there is a group of analyzers
and there's a group of builders and of
course their own they're old and this is
not as binary of course there's a whole
range in between the two and and then
that then there's everybody
complaining that everybody else is
calling to sell themselves data
scientist there's that so there's
definitely a lot of a lot of hype about
this term especially if you combine it
with the term big data which I don't
like very much but I don't think that
there's no denying in that there is that
recently certain things have come
together in a field that we call data
science which is only becoming more and
more popular what do you think that is
happening now because the ideas data
analysis has been there for a very long
time and so with statistics and even our
is already a relatively old programming
language why do you think it's in
fashion now what has created this hype
as you call it hmm so indeed many of the
techniques and ideas that are in use in
data science when you work with data are
years several years or several decades
old and in recent times what has changed
is the amount of data that we are
collecting and the amount of computing
power that we have I think those two
together they allow for new techniques
to be used
take for example deep learning which has
which is yet another very popular thing
within artificial intelligence and and
data science in recent years but the
ideas on which it's built has been
around for much much longer I think now
now that we're able to process so many
data also with the arrival of GPUs yeah
all of all of a sudden this is this is
starting to become really really popular
companies are starting to notice that
this is an important thing to have that
they should have data scientists entire
teams of data scientists data scientists
entire departments and in turn
others have noticed that there are high
salaries associated with this I think
yeah it's yeah when you have a critical
mass if companies are interested in an
education getting interested in it and
then it sort of adds up three times yeah
education is another good example in the
US but also here in the Netherlands we
see more and more education forming
around data science there are masters of
data science nowadays bachelors of data
science are coming up as well so once
again it's interesting to see that both
academia and business are moving in this
another topic of course that's quite
halts and we had an se radio show about
it show 286 is machine learning and you
already mentioned machine learning
earlier and also do just mentioned deep
learning how is data science related to
machine learning yes I think in a
similar fashion that statistics is
related to data science in fact you
could consider machine learning to be
statistics on steroids so combined
statistics right with all this computing
power and data to learn from and so if
we go back to the awesome model then the
letter and since we're modeling and this
is exactly where machine learning comes
in to play sometimes there it dars
machine learning algorithms can be used
to clean up your data for example when
you have outliers right very extreme
values in your data or when you want to
reduce the number of features in your
data
say for example you you have a digitized
image you have lots of values that you
need to reduce in order to work with
that that's another area where machine
learning yeah can come into play yeah
nice I like this quote did machine
learning is statistics on steroids that
because we have more power more
computational power more data it gets
year to do to do statistics let that
zoom in a little bit because we've
covered the big definition of data
science but suppose I want to learn data
science I'm a programmer but now I
really want to learn more about data
science what are some of the core
principles and ideas I need to learn
about so for starters I don't think that
anyone should set out to become or learn
data science instead aspire to to tackle
a certain problem that involves data and
then figure out which skills you need to
acquire in order to solve that problem
again because it is so it is so broad
there are skills relevant skills that
that fall in the category of of data
manipulation data engineering up to data
visualization again statistics there are
people who are better at machine
learning others are better communicators
there is no no typical data scientist
that's why you usually see these these
data scientists working in teams because
because you need all those skills right
very often but nobody has all these
skills equally well-developed
nevertheless if you want to learn more
about data science I I do have a couple
of books perhaps that are interesting to
read depending on where you're coming
from and taking into account that this
audience are mostly engineers one book
that I then there are a couple of Python
based data science books that I
particularly like one is called
Python for data analysis by wes mckinney
it assumes python this really goes into
some popular packages that are used
within the Python ecosystem such as
numpy side pipe
and us and so forth another book that I
like is data signs from scratch by Joel
gross and I like this book because it
uses pure Python and then and then
builds up several kinds of algorithms so
mostly machine learning algorithms for
classification and regression and so
forth now from scratch as as the title
implies if you want to move more into
machine learning per se then I could
recommend Python machine learning by
Sebastian Rushka covers mostly a package
called scikit-learn Python package which
contains a lot of algorithms and and
related tools and techniques for doing
machine learning in Python so but this
is all assuming that you have Python as
your go-to language right so so of
course there are well there are
basically too many resources MOOCs if
that is your thing right if you if you
like to watch videos and do those
exercises you know and to be honest I've
never followed a MOOC myself so I maybe
it's it's just best if you if you google
for this it sure ya will at least make
sure we will include the links to those
books you mentioned in the show notes so
if you want to check out those then
we'll definitely make sure that it's
easy for those lists for the audience to
get to those books yeah there is there's
one resource that III could mention and
this is there is a woman called Renee I
forgot her last name but she has a
Twitter account becoming data SCI or
becoming a data scientist and also data
signs Renee if I'm not mistaken but she
she aspired to become a data scientist a
couple of years ago and she has been
documenting this this entire process and
I'm sure she has
much more resources that I could ever
come up with so we'll include a link
yeah will include link now I've heard
you mentioned Python a bunch of times
and all those resources so let's talk
programming languages all right are you
endorsing Python here as the best
programming language for data science or
is there something else out there the
answer is no I'm well well I can
certainly endorse Python but it's not
the best language okay let's make it a
little bit more abstract then what are
characteristics that a programming
language has to be good for data science
ordering there are several languages and
again it depends on whether you are
analyzing or whether you are building so
let's look at analyzing when you're
analyzing you need to be able to play
with your data you need to be exploring
what your data looks like you need to be
able to quickly make visualizations
summary statistics and then move on so
this is a very ad hoc way of working
with your data in that sense I I think
it's important to have a language that
gets out of your way that doesn't that
doesn't let you worry too much about
typing about boilerplates about
instantiating all these classes upfront
right so languages like Java aren't not
suitable in my opinion to do analysis
languages that are suitable for this is
Python and are these two languages I
would consider them scripting languages
because you can you can accomplish
something in one line of code right and
this is this is what you want you want
to be able to with minimal typing you
want to get you want to get results also
what these languages offer is is a
rattle is a read eval print loop so that
you can try out individual commands see
what the outcome is and move on from
there now you would for those two
languages you would rarely work on the
repple that they offer themselves so for
python many people tend to work in
Jupiter notebook but it's a it's a
similar idea where you can execute
individual code cells and this could be
one line or a couple of lines or an
entire function and what's nice about
Jupiter notebooks is that you don't you
not only have your code but you also
have the output of that code and
intertwined in between the code cells so
this could be a result a table it could
be a figure this could be regular text
with markdown text right so in this this
really allows you to to build up this
this this document for your analysis
yeah so our audience might not be
exactly familiar with what a jupiter
notebook is is that is it like a wrapper
or is it something they're friends so a
Jupiter notebook runs in your browser
and what you see is first you see this
little gray area in which you can type
Python code so you would your you would
do your import of your of the packages
that you want to use and then you can
execute individual code cells so you
don't have to write up your entire
program and then run it and then go back
to the original code now you stay within
the same environment and you can iterate
from there so it's a and because you
have your results immediately beneath
the code you you immediately get
feedback and then you can move on from
there so you build up your code
incrementally and this is a very
different approach from coding something
optionally haven't having to compile it
and then run it from scratch right this
is this breaks your workflow yeah and
that for me still very much sounds like
Apple the way I see it I think is a
difference is that in a wrapper the
output would mainly be text only be text
whereas a notebook
you could also have different things as
output am i correct yes that's correct
so it's not just text
it's your statistical data visualization
may be a simple as histogram it could be
as complex as an HTML widget which shows
you a an interactive map of something so
and this is possible because it runs in
the browser if you're working in the
repple from the command line then the
the output is is by a necessity text
yeah yeah although there are flavors in
between those two yeah now you could
always use text of course as a
visualization by using something like an
ASCII table oh yeah yes of course that's
not as nice as a Jupiter notebook where
you have nice visualization and graphs
and charting an R so something something
that we should to talk more about as
well because these two languages are
both really popular offers something
similar called our markdown and our
markdown notebooks there the experience
is slightly different but conceptually
you have your code chunks of code cells
and the output in between those code
size yeah let's talk about our a little
bit more because I guess most of our
audience is familiar with Python or
other scripting languages but it's a
little bit different in that it is a
programming language EPM a
general-purpose programming name which
is a programming language that has a
narrow scope which is statistics and
machine learning is that correct that is
entirely correct
so R was created by statisticians for
statisticians and because of that it has
certain characteristics make which may
seem odd at first to two programmers who
are more accustomed to a language like
Java or Python but because it was
created by statisticians it is it has
become a very popular language with
indeed within the data science community
in fact I think that arm Python are the
two most popular programming language
are they in the end you can do you can
do pretty much the same with the - but
Python to me this is very personal to me
feels more like the programming language
and is also easier to understand as a
programming language and and and and and
because it started out as a programming
language Python that is it has a much
broader scope when you look at its
packages and if you look at pi pi the
repository for all Python packages it's
not just data science in fact most of it
is not data science and is also covers
anything from API development to
building your own web server creating
your own game authentication interacting
with databases and so forth are on the
other hand has last time I checked
nearly 12,000 packages as well so that's
not a short and not a small number but
it's mostly geared towards working with
data recently this has changed somewhat
our is getting a better support for
working with databases creating your own
API if you wanted to and because it is
it operates more on a on a higher level
if you if you work with a with a package
in our it offers very convenient
functions it feels to me it feels
smoother to work with our but when I'm
working in Python it it it feels more
like I'm creating this robust piece of
software again this is entirely personal
and the choice between the two
dependence well first of all on your
personal preference but more often what
are the others in your team using or
other team so I I once created this
great model for a client it was able to
do some sort of classification and now
we wanted to move that into production
meaning it had to be
it had to serve an API with which the
the website would integrate with so I
had to talk to the API team where this
was a large telecommunications company
well well long story short I had to
reimplemented thing in Python that was
not a big issue but it goes well it's an
example that when you want to do things
in production Python is most often the
better choice yeah but as you said
sometimes you don't have the choice so
suppose we have to work with are you
just mentions that it has some old
characteristics can you name a few that
we should be prepared for if you are
working in a team that's working with
our AR has a different way of working
with memory so it copies on change and
people who are first getting familiar
with with our who or already know
another programming language tend to use
a lot of for loops right to grow
incrementally build up their their data
frame which is a very important data
structure it's like a table and this
this causes memory issues right this is
this is one example it has a different
way of looking up values of variables it
and this is actually something that is
an advantage I would say of our is that
for a lot of functions you don't need to
quote your values and this may seem like
a like a trivial thing so let's say you
have some data from a long table with
rows and columns and you need to refer
to one of those columns then in Python
if you would do this using the pandas
package you need to quote everything
that's because that's simply how the
programming language works but in our
it's a technique called non-standard
evaluation you can you can simply write
those those column names without quotes
and this again may seem like a trivial
thing but it makes working with the
language and work
with their data just a little bit easier
more comfortable yeah so to summarize
our is closer to the world of
statistician and make some things easier
however it's not a fool programming
language there Python might be more
suitable if you want to do a broader
range of things yeah I would say in a
nutshell that is that is true but but it
is good to know a little bit of both
and know which one would work best for a
particular project and then decide based
on the requirements of that project and
people we are we are gonna work with
yeah of course sometimes you just don't
have the choice yeah it is good to be
informed yeah yeah okay that's enough I
think about programming languages
because your book is called data science
on the command line which maybe
indicates we don't necessarily need a
programming language there's enough we
can do on the command line what are
things we can do in the command line can
you share a few things that we can do
there without a programming language
yeah yeah so it remains to me after it's
been out now for three years rate
remains to me an odd juxtaposition of
terms on one end we have this young
field as we've discussed called data
science and the audio on the other hand
we have technology that's over 40 years
old
and I I decided to put those two
together in a book because the command
line well it offers a repple right this
read eval print loop so we can we can
type our commands and immediately get a
result but other another reason why the
command line works so nice it because is
because it has all these little
command-line tools which are designed to
do one thing but do it really well and
since they are all working with with a
text interface they can work together
really well and this this gives you a
lot of flexibility and as a result
you're able to you have to
it could be depending on your problem
that you're able to get it done with
just one or two lines at the command
line which would otherwise take you say
10 to 20 lines of code in Python or R so
you mentioned there are a few cool
command-line tools can you give some
examples of tools you could use on the
command line yeah there are many of them
in the book alone discusses over 80
command line tools and a couple of tools
that I like well first of all let's curl
is of course well it's the Swiss Army
knife of downloading things from the
internet so that would cover the
obtaining data in a lot of cases if you
want to if you're working with with JSON
data let's say you're querying some API
then that JQ is a command line tool that
and that has come out in a few years ago
that is particularly suited for this if
you want to speed up your your pipeline
say you want to distribute it among
multiple cores or machines then the new
parallel is a very yeah effective tool
for doing that let's see now if you
still happen to be working with XML I
can recommend
XML starlett if you need to scrape HTML
right sticking to obtaining data right
let's say there's no API available you
need to scrape you need to extract
certain elements from HTML then PUC is
interesting and you know those are just
a couple of examples now it's perhaps
also good that we include a link to a
docker image that I created for my book
which contains all these command line
tools and that that way you don't have
to spend
an entire day installing all these tools
one that just came to mind is CSV kit
which is a suite of command line tools
related that are able to work with CSV
data and actually I should I have I have
an interesting announcement to make
go ahead we love scoops and and that is
that my book data science at the
command-line is now available online for
free to read so I'm very happy about
that my myself so if you go to data
science at the command line com you can
you can now see an HTML version of the
book awesome we'll be sure to include
that in the show notes as well and also
the docker image you mentioned that will
save people a lot of work if they want
to explore this so how do you go about
this suppose you have some fluency with
all these command line tools how do you
package them together in a working thing
and by a working thing I guess you also
want something that is somewhat robust
somewhat producible yeah this is
actually the especially rep reducible is
where I was going because if I have a
Python file I run then if I get new data
I can run the file again but if I do it
only come online it it's gone if I close
the command line how do you deal with
that exactly that robustness and that
reproducibility that would come
automatically if you would have a Python
file right so in these when you when you
start working at the command line it's
it's it's typing commands and then well
they tend to be gone right there's no
you're not working in the script just
yet but to a certain extent this is this
is still possible you can go back into
your history collect all the commands
that make sense clean them up put them
in a in a script that would work for
short scripts that are designed for very
specific tasks maybe you would include
some bash programming but as soon as I
get to as soon as I need some more logic
in my script I tend to go to a
programming language myself and that
whether that's our Python right that
depends
but yeah the command line is definitely
not suited for everything it's
especially when you're in that that
first phase you just got a new data set
you have no idea what it is and you need
to yeah you need to quickly have a look
at things compute some things count
certain lines I don't know maybe you're
working with log files of some server
right which has nothing installed that
would be a good use case that's where
the command line can really shine but as
soon as you want to build something that
is robust that you want to maybe even
share with your colleagues I would that
you want something reproducible and that
you understand six months down the line
I I would use a programming language in
those cases yeah so to come online if
you were talking about the awesome model
again would be early in the awesome all
the way you're obtaining scrubbing and
exploring data as soon as your start
modeling and analyzing you would go to a
real programming in front right mostly
just the good thing is most times you
can go back and forth in between the two
it's if you look at an entire data
science project it's composed of all
these little subproblems and it's up to
you to decide which tool gets to jumped
on best right whether that is the
command line or Jupiter notebook or pen
and paper doesn't matter but as long as
long as you get the job done so what
you're arguing I think is no do all your
stuff from the command line but more be
aware that there are these awesome tools
on the command line that can help you do
things more efficiently but don't use
them forever no no let's talk about that
robustness and reproducibility a little
bit more because I think there are some
interesting angles that make data
science different from so FRA
developments for example how do you go
about version control
your version controlling in so far and
you just have your source code whereas I
think if you're doing data nets if you
have to do version control of your
source code but also of your data
because if your data changed in the
meantime but you're running it with the
same source code you might still get
different results are there specific
things or specific methodologies you use
in doing version control in data science
or is it just a regular software project
project and you do everything similar I
think ideally you would you would tend
to use or you would you would adopt the
best practices that engineering has
already come up with such as version
control and it's it's of course
perfectly fine to version your control
your code your data on the other hand I
wouldn't I wouldn't put my data in a
github repository first aid rather I
would have the code that gets the data
whether that is from some API or some
database I would have that part of my
code so that is also versioned you want
to eliminate all these manual steps so
that it's it's not a matter of okay I I
can interact with this database using
Excel and then I just need to change a
few columns here let's export this to
CSV and then my script can run no you
want to version control all the things
yeah sure all the things yes
what I was thinking I mean you have this
data set and you run your analysis and
you say okay we have to you know buy
this stocks or sell these stocks and the
next day your boss comes in says okay
show me how you got this results if you
use a tool that just scrapes data maybe
you get a different result a slightly
different result
do you somehow want to track what data
you ran what analysis on and how would
you do that or you're saying there is no
such thing as yesterday's data we didn't
care about that anymore we just run the
whole analysis based on fresh theta and
that is a new conclusion interesting
point in that sense I would I would
definitely make a copy of that of
yesterday's data
and make sure that the code is able to
accept a parameter such as from and to
yeah no it is a very important friend
reminded working as a data scientist in
2012 at a start-up in New York and when
I when I came down was the first data
scientist I noticed that all the
engineers were throwing away all the raw
data right so I mean I I don't blame
them I mean data storing all that data
is expensive and they were computing
aggregate statistics to report to our
our customers and and that's that but
well of course as a data scientist I I
decided to to change that and to make
sure that all the raw data was was
properly backed up and so that we could
redo or backtracking or back tracing
it's I believe it's sometimes called
that you're able to run your algorithm
on all the data as well it could be that
you're improving your existing algorithm
especially with machine learning
algorithms is it this might be the case
and you want to compare multiple
versions of that algorithm against the
whole period of data so so having those
two parameters if from an a to actually
makes them makes a lot of sense yeah so
generalizing from them that from that
that programmer software engineer that
would become a data scientist or do more
with data science probably has to change
our mindset a little bit into seeing
data especially raw data as something
that's important because if you were
sober engineer you're probably mainly
focused on the code and not so much on
the day as exactly as you're describing
and that's it's important I think to
keep in mind if you would move more
towards becoming a data scientist yeah
yeah that's that's where both groups if
we can make that harsh this yeah I know
it's a spectrum but that's where they
can learn a lot that's where they can
learn from each other
I believe that they data scientists
don't learn a lot from data for from
engine years when it comes to coding
styles version control documentation
packaging all those kind of things and
so and I'm sure there are plenty of
things that engineers can also learn
from data scientists here's something
you haven't mentioned in the long list
of things they could learn from us to
make the distinction even more clear
it's testing so if you were data
scientists how do you go about testing
your models of course you have your real
data to test certain assumptions own but
are there things do you write unit tests
or integration tests if you're a data
scientist how does that work hmm so I
believe there are several types of
testing in the machine learning world
when you say testing what you usually or
what you do is that you divide all the
data that you have all the labeled data
so let's say you have lots of API calls
with a certain label like valid or
invalid or you have a whole bunch of
fruit saying okay this is an apple and
there's an orange what you then do is
you divide this data set into a training
set and a test set you train a model on
the training set and you test it you let
it make predictions on the test set and
then you compare the outcome from the
machine learning algorithm to those
through labels right valid invalid API
call or apples and oranges when it comes
to fruit and that will lead to a certain
performance that is one type of testing
but then you're talking about is
algorithm a better than algorithm B when
you said unit testing that's a that's a
different kind of testing but important
nonetheless there well I would use say
mock data right you you have a certain
set of data on which you know the
outcome may be not necessarily the nth
predictions but may be
intermediate computations as well and
that would be a way to to check whether
the code whether your algorithm is still
working correctly and is this something
that's not in practice well it's unit
testing done a lot and in software
that's not really what are you talking
about
well it's it's one of those things that
data scientists are really fond of it's
kind of like a documentation thing it
should be done more often yeah
definitely yeah a final form of testing
or on their main forms but something
else it might be interesting is is
regression testing understanding
especially since the code might be
stable but you're getting more and more
data which is changing your model is
this something that's done checking what
way a model is going with automated
tests I mean you yourself said automate
all the things mm-hmm so regressions are
so-so tracking the performance of your
algorithm in the long run yeah and then
it could be performance in the sense how
long is it taking to compute something
right that's more from an engineering
point of view and the other thing that
you probably want to test is is it still
giving good results yeah so the first
one I would say is is is quite
straightforward well you can measure how
long an algorithm is taking and if you
then store that raw data as well well
then you can do some analysis on that of
course whether the algorithm is still
making the right predictions
still has a good performance in the long
run that's it that's a very difficult
subject and especially when this
algorithm has an effect on the real
world right which tends to feedback yeah
into itself and it could be could be
that because of this algorithm the data
the things that you observe of your your
your your users and your customers that
that is changing and so I don't really
have an answer for this yeah but it's
it's
a complicated thing there is it there is
an important paper related to this aisle
I will include the link to that one
about regression testing machine
learning yeah about the the side effects
that machine learning can have I if I'm
not mistaken it's called the technical
debt of machine learning could be
somewhat different well look it up okay
we'll look it up and we'll make sure
that it's in the show notes one more
thing you said about documentation that
made me think about open source because
lots of software of course is nowadays
open sources I'm good up people can see
what is happening even sometimes within
companies or within organizations do you
see similar movements in data science
where these data science models are also
shared as open source such that they can
be reused and then also document says
all these things mainly happening in
companies that don't want to share their
data analysis models okay so let's
distinguish between the tools and
techniques to build such a model and the
models themselves
first of all in general I definitely see
a positive trend towards open source
within data science that's also why
Python and are both open source
languages have become so popular right
and all the commercial software is
losing this battle like who's losing
MATLAB for example during my PhD or 75%
of it I was using MATLAB and I would say
I had it took me a while but I realized
that once I got out of outside of
academia it's not used that much at all
which is not that surprising if you
consider the how expensive it is to use
these days yeah people who want to learn
something will will will tend to go for
for the option that is that is free
freely available that is open source so
if companies are looking for four for
smart people to hire with a certain
expertise or an experience they will
most of the time have experienced with
what with things that are open-source
and less often with something that is
expensive and commercial also with with
open-source there tends to be a bigger
community around it if you if you look
at the all the communities around Python
and are those are so much bigger again
then what commercial counterparts have
at this moment and I think that this
will only become more and more clear and
then we'll open source models well that
is typically something that a company is
not so willing to share and with model
you mean the results of the Python
scripts or our script or also the script
itself the former so they're so they
have typically some data that they have
collected they have applied an algorithm
to it which produced a model and this
could be their competitive advantage
like to do something and so they in that
sense they could be willing to share the
code that led to that model but not the
model itself and do they typically do
share the code that led to the model is
this something that happens or are those
things also felt to be proprietary mmm
you do see more often that the big
companies like Facebook and Microsoft
and Twitter that they are sharing
algorithms right and and also and maybe
even pre trained models but is this is
definitely not everything that they are
using for example language models that
that have been trained on lots and lots
of data every now and then you do see
that these companies share share those
models but more often they share the
underlying code that generated that for
example Facebook
open sourced a package which is
available for both R and Python
interestingly enough called profit which
allows you to make forecasts based on
time series III like this package a lot
and I think it is great that a that a
company like like Facebook is willing to
share that with with everybody else yeah
and then there this is just one example
of many so there is some sharing going
on in terms of source code but obviously
not the data and often not the Train
models mostly yeah more often than not
those the data is kept kept secret you
do you do tend to see more open data but
yeah those are those are exceptions yeah
okay that's everything I wanted to ask
thanks a lot for being on the show my
pleasure
if the audience wants to know more where
can they learn more from you alright
well I'm on Twitter for starters we will
add the link to the show now at least
it's too too difficult to pronounce
sexually that handle and if you think
okay I want to learn more about data
science oh you're not alone you're with
an entire team within your company then
it's worthwhile to note that I also give
workshops in these kind of things
workshops in R and then Python or how to
use the command line for doing data
science and if you would like more
information about that the website is
data science workshops comm which we
will of course also include in show
notes and also a link to your book that
is again freely available for everyone
yeah anything else ok thanks again for
being on the show
this was Felina for SE radio thanks for
listening to se radio an educational
program brought to you by Triple E
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at SE - radio net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack channel at SC radio.com you
can also email us a team at SC - radio
net this and all other episodes of se
radio is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening